Guide to the William D. Hardin Papers, 1838-1946 RL.10115
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William D. Hardin papers
1838-1946
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hardin, William D.
RL.10115
2.5 Linear Feet 5 boxes, 905 items.
Collection includes personal, business, and legal papers (chiefly 1870-1900), relating to retail merchandising, education, religion, politics, Masonry, flour milling, and agriculture in Guilford County, N.C. Includes school registers, students' letters and references to the Battle of Hatcher's Run, Va. (Feb. 5-7, 1865) and to conditions in the Union and Confederate armies at that time.
Collection Overview
Collection contains personal, business, and legal papers (chiefly 1870-1900), relating to retail merchandising, education, religion, politics, Masonry, flour milling, and agriculture in Guilford County, N.C. Includes school registers, students' letters and references to the Battle of Hatcher's Run, Va. (Feb. 5-7, 1865) and to conditions in the Union and Confederate armies at that time.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William D. Hardin Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1959.
Collection Overview
This collection contains mainly business and personal letters, bills, and receipts of William D. Hardin and family, and William Henry Ragan, dealing for the most part with local affairs, including legal matters, retail merchandising, education, religion, politics, Masonry, flour milling, and farming. Volumes include four registers for common school districts in Guilford County, North Carolina, 1879-1895. school notebooks; minute book of Pleasant Garden Farmers' Alliance, No. 2195, of Guilford County; and a poll book, 1924, for Fentriss Precinct, Guilford County.
Many of the bills and receipts deal with the merchansiding and manufacturing firms with which Hardin and Ragan were connected. They bought much from merchants in Richmond and northward. A number of items deal with guano imported from Peru. The legal papers, running from 1863 to 1920, consist mainly of Justice of the Peace summonses, affidavits, executions of judgment, powers of attorney, indentures, contracts to build and repair a stock fence betweem Randolph and Guilford counties, and deeds. The eight election papers deal with miscellaneous election matters, an item, circa 1884, lists congressional and other candidates. The 15 items of printed matter include an 1870 circular of the New Garden Boarding School, New Garden, North Carolina, an 1882 notice of a Guilford County Republican meeting, and an 1889 act of the North Carolina General Assembly to incorporate the Farmer's State Alliance. The 11 bound volumes range from 1879 to 1924. Four are registers for common school districts in Guilford County (1879-1895). One is a poll book (1924) for the Fentriss Precinct. There is another volume (1886-1889) used as a daybook and time book.
[Added Information from copy of original catalog cards.]
Biographical Note
William D. Hardin was an activist Methodist layman, he served as Justice of the Peace during much, if not all, of the time from 1878 to 1901. He was church secretary and as a chairman of a church board in 1895, and was on a committee of the Guilford County Sabbath School Association. He seems for a time to have served on the school board and to have operated retail stores off and on. He was a Masonic Lodge secretary in 1872 and 1875 and perhaps at other times as well. In 1896 and 1898 he was a tax list taker in Fentriss, North Carolina and was a register for political elections (time and place unknown). In 1891 and 1895 he was vice-president of the Pleasant Gardens Farmer's Alliance, No. 2195 of Guilford County. He was president of the Julian Milling Company of Jullian, North Carolina in 1899-1900.
Agriculture -- North Carolina -- Guilford County.; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Guilford County (N.C.) -- Politics and government; Guilford County (N.C.) -- Commerce; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns; Guilford County (N.C.) -- Religion; Merchants -- North Carolina -- Guilford County; Flour mills -- North Carolina -- Guilford County; Students -- North Carolina -- Guilford County; Schools -- North Carolina -- Guilford County; United States. Army -- Military life; Confederate States of America. Army -- Military life; Freemasons. Grand Lodge of North Carolina; Hardin, William D.
- William D. Hardin papers, 1838-1946
  - Letters, 1856-1885 (Box 1)
  - Bills and receipts, 1870-1879 (Box 2)
  - Legal papers, 1863-1920 and undated (Box 2)
  - Election papers, 1884 and undated (Box 2)
  - Printed materials, 1870-1915 and undated (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1886-1946 and undated (Box 3)
  - Bills and receipts, 1870-1879 (Box 3)
  - Papers, misc., 1879-1890 (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1891-1924 and undated (Box 5)